In this demo, we'll be creating a program that utilizes looping.
Once you're ready, fire up Visual Studio Code, and let's go.
Once Visual Studio Code loads, click on the demo folder.
We're on the Loops demo, so scroll down to Loops,
click that, and then double click on Loops.go.
We'll be creating a basic for loop,
and we'll take the iterator value and add it together
to create a sum.
So the first thing we need to do is create a sum variable,
and we'll set it to be equal to zero.
We'll then do a print line that way when we run the program.
We know what the sum is when we start the program.
We'll then create our for loop by creating a new i variable,
and set it to the value of one.
As long as i is less than or equal to 10,
we'll increment it by one and run the loop.
Within the loop, we'll take sum, and we'll add i to it.
Each loop iteration will print out some is, and we'll print the sum.
So in our code, we're creating a new i variable for this for loop,
and we're setting it to be equal to one.
And as long as i is less than or equal to 10,
we'll execute the body of this loop.
Whenever this loop body executes and gets to the end,
i will be incremented by one, and it'll be checked again for this condition.
And once i is greater than 10, this will evaluate two false,
then we'll exit out and continue running the program.
Within our loop body, we take the sum, which is initially zero,
and we add i to it.
i starts at one, so first will be plus one, then plus two,
then plus three, all the way until i is 10.
Before we continue, let's run this program,
and we'll see what kind of output that we get.
Someone hop into a terminal.
We can run this program with go, run dot slash demo slash loops.
And we can see the output starts at zero, one, three,
and then eventually we end up at 55.
We hop back into the code.
We're not going to create another loop,
and as long as the sum is greater than 10,
we'll take the sum minus equals five,
and then we'll print it out.
And we'll also note that we're having a decrement operation
that we know that which loop that we're in.
So with this loop, we don't create a new variable at all.
All we're doing is checking if the sum is greater than 10.
We know from the last run that the sum was 55,
so it's definitely greater than 10,
and this will check out as true.
We'll then enter into this loop.
We'll take the sum, which is 55,
or minus five from it, and then it'll get reassigned back into sum.
We'll then print out a message that we're documenting,
and then the loop will continue.
And this condition is going to keep being checked
until sum is finally less than 10,
or less than or equal to 10.
So let's save and run this program,
and we'll see what we get.
So here we have at the top, it won't have the screen,
but we started one, and then we end up at 55,
and now we decrement five at a time.
So 50, 45, 40, all the way down until the sum is 10.
One particular thing to remember about this loop down here on the bottom
is we aren't changing the sum within the loop statement itself.
So here in this for loop, this first one,
we have the i plus plus at the end,
which modifies this i,
which eventually affects this condition.
None of that is present here on this bottom loop,
so if we forget to subtract or add to the sum,
then this will just go on forever,
because 55 is greater than 10,
and so this is always going to be true,
and this will just be an infinite loop.
So always remember to have something that modifies this expression
that way the loop eventually terminates.
This concludes the demo on loops.
I'll see you in the next presentation.